<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ds="eml://ecoinformatics.org/dataset-2.1.0" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0&#10;&#9;&#9;&#9;&#9;http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd" packageId="knb-lter-bnz.428.11" system="knb" scope="system">
<access scope="document" order="allowFirst" authSystem="knb">
<allow>
<principal>uid=BNZ,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<shortName>knb-lter-bnz.428.11</shortName>
<title>Eight Mile Lake gradient sites: Growing season CO2 fluxes and several ecosystem measurements taken during the growing season of 2006 and 2007.</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Hanna</givenName>
<surName>Lee</surName>
</individualName>
<positionName>Graduate Student</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, 214 Bartram Hall, University of Florida</deliveryPoint>
<city>Gainsville</city>
<administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>32611-8526</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">(352) 392-9620</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">(352) 392-3993</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>hannalee@ufl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<!--No personal web address info on file-->
</creator>
<metadataProvider>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</metadataProvider>
<associatedParty>
<individualName>
<givenName>Edward</givenName>
<givenName>A.G.</givenName>
<surName>Schuur</surName>
</individualName>
<positionName>Associate Professor</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>University of Florida Department of Botany 220 Bartram Hall</deliveryPoint>
<city>Gainesville</city>
<administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>32611</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">(352) 392-7913</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">(352) 392-3993</phone>
<role>Associated investigator</role>
</associatedParty>
<pubDate>2010-03-01</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>This dataset contains growing season CO2 fluxes, aboveground biomass, soil temperature, volumetric moisture content, seasonal thaw depth, and NDVI measured at 50 grid points along EML gradient sites measured . </para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>thermokarst</keyword>
<keyword>fluxes</keyword>
<keyword>upscaling</keyword>
<keyword>respiration</keyword>
<keyword>carbon dioxide</keyword>
<keyword>microtopography</keyword>
<keyword>permafrost</keyword>
<keyword>soil temperature</keyword>
<keyword>soil moisture</keyword>
<keyword>biomass</keyword>
<keyword>net ecosystem exchange</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Biogeochemistry</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights>
<section>
<title>Access to Data</title>
<para>While metadata will be freely available to those requesting it, the data manager will assure that any restrictions on access to data sets in the database will be enforced. Data will not be released without proper permission first being obtained from the investigator who generated the data. </para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Use of data</title>
<para> Researchers should receive adequate acknowledgment for the use of their data by others and should be provided with copies of publications using their data. Users of data from the data base must be aware that data is not to be sold or redistributed.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Citing Bonanza Creek LTER Datasets</title>
<para>It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. </para>
</section>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution id="distributionReference">
<online>
<url function="information">http://www.lter.uaf.edu/data_detail.cfm?datafile_pkey=428</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage id="geoReference">
<geographicDescription>Site information unavailable</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-149.2535833</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.2535833</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>63.87836111</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>63.87836111</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2006-06-25</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2008-08-10</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
</coverage>
<maintenance>
<description>
<section>
<title>Status</title>
<para>Completed</para>
</section>
</description>
</maintenance>
<contact>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<positionName>Data Manager</positionName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>uaf-bnz-im-team@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<onlineUrl>http://www.lter.uaf.edu</onlineUrl>
</contact>
<publisher>
<organizationName>Bonanza Creek LTER</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>Boreal Ecology Cooperative Research Unit </deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of Alaska Fairbanks</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 756780 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Fairbanks</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99775</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">907-474-6364</phone>
<phone phonetype="fax">907-474-6251</phone>
</publisher>
<pubPlace>Bonanza Creek LTER</pubPlace>
<methods>
<methodStep>
<description>
<section>
<title>Experimental Design</title>
<para>This is a tundra site that shows gradient of permafrost thaw and thermokarst development.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Methods</title>
<para>Land surface survey: As a preliminary study, we surveyed the landscape to quantify surface subsidence created by permafrost thaw and thermokarst at the three EML gradient sites in 2004. Fine scale ground subsidence was estimated using Theodolite Total Station surveying equipment (Leica TPS400, Leica Geosystems, St. Gallen, Switzerland). Approximately 12 transects were established within a 50 m × 50 m area at each site and 600 (± 50) points were surveyed within each site. Sampling points along a single transect were spaced approximately 50 cm apart. Tussocks were avoided to minimize variations in surface topography not directly due to thermokarst; all topography measurements represent the moss/soil surface. The x, y, z (Longitude, Latitude, Altitude) coordinates were then normalized for hill slope trends along the z-axis to minimize the topographical shape of the hill slope. In order to isolate microtopography as a result of thermokarst, we obtained means of the highest 10% of the points per site, excluding the top 5% of the z-axis measurements to minimize the impact of outliers. All of the z-axis values were normalized according to the mean of these highest 10% values as a measure of surface subsidence. This procedure was done separately for each site with the idea that the highest elevation measurements (after hillslope detrending) approximated the pre-subsidence surface. Therefore, the surfaces with lower relative elevation largely represent surface subsidence created by permafrost thaw and thermokarst development, whereas the surfaces with higher relative elevation represent elevated surfaces that did not subside (Schuur et al., 2009). This relative elevation measurement representing surface subsidence created by permafrost thaw and thermokarst development will be referred to as ‘microtopography (MT)’ throughout this study. Measurement grid establishment: In 2006, a subset of the surveyed area was established as measurement grid points at each EML gradient site (Figure 1) to quantify ecosystem variables such as soil temperature, moisture, thaw depth, and aboveground biomass as well as ecosystem CO2 fluxes (GPP, Reco, and NEE), and to relate these measurements to microtopography. These measurements encompassed an equally spaced 5 m grid within a 50 m × 25 m area, so that there were 50 sampling points per Minimal, Moderate, and Extensive Thaw site (hereafter ‘50 grid points’). We used differential Global Positioning Systems (GPS) to determine the location and topographical surface features of the 50 grid points at the EML gradient sites. We were also interested in fine scale topographical features, since the differential GPS method provides precision up to 1 vertical centimeter (Little et al., 2003). One GPS unit (Trimble 5400) was installed at a nearby USGS marker (WGS84, 63º53'16.56"N, 149º14'17.92"W) and the other GPS unit was used to measure the coordinates of interest. Measurements were corrected relative to the marker to obtain better accuracy. The longitude and latitude information collected from the differential GPS and the Theodolite Total Station was converted to the Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) coordinate system using ArcGIS 9.3 (ESRI, 2008).  Soil properties: Soil temperature sensors were deployed in a manner that captured the spatial variability in soil temperature at the 50 grid points within the EML gradient sites. IButton Thermochron temperature loggers (Maxim Inc., Dallas, TX) were buried at each grid point to a depth of 10 cm and temperature was logged for three days in continuous 30 min intervals. Mean soil temperatures at 10 cm depths were obtained for the three days of measurements and normalized within a measurement period. Higher soil temperature estimated from this normalization indicated that soil temperature at a particular microsite was higher than the mean of the 50 grid points. These observations were used to describe spatial variability of soil temperature. 
Soil thaw depth (TD) was measured during the peak of the growing season (mid-July) in 2006 and 2007 at each of the 50 grid points. Depth from the surface was recorded using a 1/16” rod that was pushed into the ground until it hit the frozen layer. Soil moisture content was measured by volumetric water content (VWC) using a Campbell Scientific CS616 water content reflectometer and a hand-held voltmeter at 10 cm depths in the soil at each of the 50 grid points. The CS616 was calibrated for the EML gradient sites at nearby points using direct sampling of soil water content made with destructive soil sampling to compare with CS616 values made at those same nearby points (Lee et al., in press). Aboveground biomass and vegetation index:  Aboveground plant biomass was estimated for the 50 grid points within the EML gradient sites during the most productive time of the year (mid-July to early-August) in 2006 using the point-framing method. The point-framing method quantifies aboveground plant biomass as well as species composition. We used the same method presented in Schuur et al. (2007) and used allometric equations developed for the EML gradient sites to estimate total aboveground biomass (g m-2) of a small quadrat (40 cm × 40 cm) used in the point-framing method. We indirectly assessed vegetation biomass at the 50 grid points using the normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI), which was measured at the same time aboveground biomass was estimated using the point-framing method. The NDVI is an estimate of vegetation cover measured by the differences between near infrared radiation (NIR) and visible wavelength (VIS) (NDVI = (NIR–VIS) / (NIR+VIS)). We used a hand-held ADC camera (Tetracam Inc., Chatsworth CA) to take photographs of the vegetation encountered in point-framing and later used Tetracam Pixel Wrench2 software (Tetracam Inc., Chatsworth CA) to process the images to estimate NDVI. Ecosystem carbon fluxes: Ecosystem CO2 fluxes were measured to estimate ecosystem respiration (Reco), gross primary production (GPP), and NEE at the 50 grid points within the EML gradient sites. NEE was estimated from measurements of CO2 fluxes under ambient light and absolute dark (NEElight = GPP – Reco; NEEdark = (–) Reco). We used a closed static chamber system to measure CO2 flux (Schuur et al., 2009) using an infra-red gas analyzer (Li-820, LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln NB), as air circulated through attached to a 40 cm × 40 cm × 40 cm plastic chamber. The flow of air was maintained at 1.5 L min-1. Light intensity was measured as photosynthetically active radiation (PAR, µmol m-2 sec-1) using a LICOR quantum sensor placed inside the chamber. To take the dark CO2 flux measurement, we blocked the light by covering the chamber with a reflective cloth designed to fit the chamber exactly. GPP and NEE were corrected by the light intensity and Reco was corrected by air temperature at 25°C. The CO2 flux was measured three times at the peak of the growing season (late July) during 2006 and 2007 and the means of the three measurements were used for further analyses of GPP, Reco, and NEE.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<sampling>
<studyExtent>
<coverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<references>geoReference</references>
</geographicCoverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2006-06-25</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2008-08-10</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
</coverage>
</studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>
<section>
<title>Sampling Frequency</title>
<para>During the peak of the growing season.</para>
</section>
</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>
<dataTable>
<entityName>428_EMLfluxes.txt</entityName>
<!--No data table description found (df_loc/df_desc)-->
<physical>
<objectName>428_EMLfluxes.txt</objectName>
<dataFormat>
<textFormat>
<numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
<recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
<physicalLineDelimiter>\n</physicalLineDelimiter>
<attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
<simpleDelimited>
<fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
</simpleDelimited>
</textFormat>
</dataFormat>
<distribution>
<online>
<url function="download">http://metacat.lternet.edu/das/dataAccessServlet?docid=knb-lter-bnz.428.11&amp;urlTail=/ascii/files/428_EMLfluxes.txt</url>
</online>
</distribution>
</physical>
<attributeList>
<attribute>
<attributeName>Site</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Site</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Each grid point at EML gradient site</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>string</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Each grid point at EML gradient site</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<!--No missing value/character in database (datafilevarible/errorcode)-->
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>Reco</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Reco</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Ecosystem respiration measured from CO2 fluxes under dark</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Ecosystem respiration measured from CO2 fluxes under dark</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>NEE</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>NEE</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Net ecosystem exchange of CO2 measured from CO2 fluxes under light</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Net ecosystem exchange of CO2 measured from CO2 fluxes under light</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>GPP</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>GPP</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>NEE = GPP - Reco</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>NEE = GPP - Reco</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>MT</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>MT</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Microtopography measured by GPS unit and Theodolite as reletive elevation corrected from top 10% as 0.</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>Microtopography measured by GPS unit and Theodolite as reletive elevation corrected from top 10% as 0.</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>NDVI</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>NDVI</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>The differences between near infrared radiation (NIR) and visible wavelength (VIS) (NDVI = (NIR–VIS) / (NIR+VIS)).</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>The differences between near infrared radiation (NIR) and visible wavelength (VIS) (NDVI = (NIR–VIS) / (NIR+VIS)).</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>TD</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>TD</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>The depth from surface to hit frozen ground measured in mid-July.</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>
<!--No minimum value recorded in database (datafilevaribles/minvalid)-->
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>VWC</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>VWC</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Soil moisture content measured with CS616.</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<customUnit>cm3/cm3</customUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>
<!--No minimum value recorded in database (datafilevaribles/minvalid)-->
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>T</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>T</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>IButton Thermochron temperature loggers (Maxim Inc., Dallas, TX) were buried at each grid point to a depth of 10 cm and temperature was logged for three days in continuous 30 min intervals. Mean soil temperatures at 10 cm depths were obtained for the three days of measurements and normalized within a measurement period. Higher soil temperature estimated from this normalization indicated that soil temperature at a particular microsite was higher than the mean of the 50 grid points. These observations were used to describe spatial variability of soil temperature.</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<ratio>
<unit>
<standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
</unit>
<numericDomain>
<numberType>real</numberType>
<!--No minimum value recorded in database (datafilevaribles/minvalid)-->
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
<attribute>
<attributeName>Biomass</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Biomass</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>aboveground biomass measured in 2006 at the peak of the growing season using pointframing method.</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale>
<nominal>
<nonNumericDomain>
<textDomain>
<definition>aboveground biomass measured in 2006 at the peak of the growing season using pointframing method.</definition>
</textDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
<missingValueCode>
<code>-9999</code>
<codeExplanation>Missing Value</codeExplanation>
</missingValueCode>
</attribute>
</attributeList>
</dataTable>
</dataset>
<additionalMetadata>
 <metadata>
 <unitList>
<unit id="cm3/cm3"/>
<unit id="umolCO2-Cm-2s-1"/>
</unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
